Guide to the Cornwall Military Collection 1754-1953 MS 019 MS 019 MS 019
Cornwall Historical Society
Cornwall Military Collection
1754-1953
Cornwall Historical Society
MS 019
2 linear feet (4 boxes)
This collection contains documents relating to Cornwall’s military history.
Provenance
This collection was begun by Cornwall historian E.C. Starr, but expanded and organized by subsequent historians and presidents of the Cornwall Historical Society, such as Emily E. Marsh and Barbara Gold.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
This collection includes materials related to Cornwall from the French and Indian, American Revolution, and Civil Wars as well as World War I, the Cold War and the antebellum era. Topics covered also include the home front, wartime agriculture, and Cornwall servicemen.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes items associated with conflicts that Cornwall residents have taken part in from the French and Indian War up to the Cold War. Information about service-people’s gravesites is also included in this collection. Primary documents, such as commissions, orders, and military receipts are found within these documents, as are published accounts relating to Cornwall veterans. This collection also contains the military papers of Edward D. Cartwright, a Cornwall business-owner and captain in the Cornwall Company of the Connecticut Home Guard during World War I.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically by conflict then chronologically within each series.
The files are grouped into series:
French and Indian War
American Revolution
Antebellum Era
Civil War
World War I
World War II
Cold War
Memorial Information
Miscellanea
World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Cold War.; nited States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States--History--French and Indian War, 1754-1763.; Agriculture.; Correspondence; Pamphlets; Articles; Cornwall Historical Society; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941; Sedgwick, John, 1813-1864.
- French and Indian War
  - Order to Fairfield County officials to procure horses and weapons for soldiers, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Signatures of Cornwall militia members who volunteered for service, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - French and Indian War diary of Ebenezer Dibble, 1759-1762 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper with transcription of Dibble’s diary, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Typed manuscript of records relating to the French and Indian War, American Revolution, and War of 1812, 1758-1819 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- American Revolution
  - List of Cornwall men who enlisted in the Connecticut militia, 1775 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Revolutionary War diary of Daniel Allen, 1776 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Copy of Noah Harrison’s appointment as 3rd sergeant, 1777 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Size Rolls of Heman Swift’s regiment, 1777-1781 (Box 1, Folder 10-Sep)
  - Transcribed list of Cornwall men who took oaths of fidelity, 1777-1781 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Invoice of clothing procured for Cornwall Continental Army soldiers, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dispositions of Cornwall soldiers captured at Fort Washington, 13-Nov (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Letter sent from Heman Swift to Judah Kellogg, about military matters, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Order sent to Seth Pierce from Ebenezer Gay, to send men to Sharon, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Order sent to Sherman Patterson from Edward Rogers, to draft Timothy Brunson, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Connecticut state report on towns’ men in the military, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Letter from Captain Thomas Tanner to Cornwall selectmen, asking for donated clothing, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Order sent to Captain Seth Pierce from Lt. Colonel Ebenezer Gay, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Invoice of clothing procured for Cornwall Continental Army soldiers, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Copy of Allen Shepard’s discharge from the British Army, with notes by E.C. Starr, 1783 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - List of men and arms captured upon General Burgoyne’s surrender, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letter sent to David Coe from the US War Department, regarding his pension, 1821 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pension form of Burritt Jennings, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper article on Daniel Bissell, spy, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - E.C. Starr correspondence regarding David Mallory, soldier, 1915-1928 (Box 1, Folder 26-29)
  - Detail of Revolutionary War-era stockings donated to the DAR by M.A. Chester, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Letter from US Dept. of the Interior, regarding war record of John Guest, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Letter from US Dept. of the Interior, regarding war records of Abel Avery, James Bierce, Daniel Harrison, and Jasper Pratt, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Advertisements for books about soldiers, undated (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Essay, “Boy from Cornwall, Connecticutt in the Rev. War,” by Timothy Stone, about Oliver Burnham’s war record, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Information on pensioner, William Russell, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - List of soldiers, Abel Avery, James Bierce, Daniel Harrison, Jasper Pratt, Oliver Burnham, Elias Hart, Titus Hart, and Hiram Whitcomb, undated (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
  - List of soldiers’ clothing, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Newspaper article, “Sharon Estate Conceals Tale of Revolution", undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Notes by E.C. Starr, undated (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
  - Short fragment regarding Ebenezer Sherwood’s service, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Antebellum Era
  - Eliakim M. Pratt’s Conn. militia appointment, 1823 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Edward R. White’s Conn. militia commission, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Judson Wells’ Conn. militia commission, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Booklet, Answer of Liet. B.S. Alexander, Corps. of Engineers, U.S.A., Architect of the United States Military Asylum, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Civil War
  - Political Items
    - Lincoln/Hamlin campaign envelope, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Letter from Selectman Russell R. Pratt to state comptroller, about allotments for soldiers’ families, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Volume published by US House of Representatives including Washington’s Farewell Address, Jackson’s Proclamation against Nullification, and the Declaration of Independence, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Memorial ribbon for “The Martyr President” Abraham Lincoln, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - State Union ticket, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Servicemen
    - Letter from a soldier to his brother and sister, attributed to the Bargan family, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letter from G.H. Bryan to cousins Joe and Janet, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Portrait of William H. Cogswell, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Portrait of Edward F. Gold, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Final statement of Lt. David A. Hoag, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Letter to state authorities from Charles H. Parmalee, regarding bounty payment, 1861 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Discharge of Philander Payne, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Copies of George Washington Vaill diaries, 1862-1864 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Receipt of T.R. Baldwin for furnishing John Williams as a substitute soldier, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - E.C. Starr Documents
    - Matthew Bell obituary, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Letter from Harriet C. Blinn, regarding Col. C.D. Blinn, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Letter from Sons of Union Veterans, regarding Israel Dibble, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence with Lt. Everett E. Dunbar, 1889-undated (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
    - Yale College commemorative booklet mentioning Rev. Jacob Eaton and Ira W. Pettibone, 1865 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence with Elizabeth Gregory, regarding Capt. J. Milton Gregory, with images, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence and notes regarding Elias Hart, also known as Edgar Hart, 1928-undated (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
    - Copy of the death certificate of Jeremiah May, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Letter from state quartermaster, regarding military headstones for Jeremiah May and David Hector, 1914 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Will of George P. North, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Account of military service by Philander T. Payne, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Capt. C.N. Roberts’ obituary, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Newspaper clippings related to Edward S. Roberts’ military career and wedding anniversary, 1917-1918 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Article, “Conn. Soldiers’ Orphan Home,” in Religious Herald, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Text of memorial speech given for Gen. John Sedgwick by William D. Bosler, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Newspaper article by T.S. Gold about story told to him by Chas. D. Blinn regarding a Confederate sword captured in LA, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Correspondence with the Sons of Union Veterans, regarding Starr’s History of Cornwall, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 35-37)
    - List of Cornwall children paid pensions after losing their fathers during the Civil War, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - List of Cornwall Revolutionary War and Civil War soldiers, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Newspaper article about Civil War prison in Salisbury, NC, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Reunion invitation sent to E.C. Starr from Jno. M. Gregory Post, No. 59, GAR, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Sheet music, “We Will Not Retreat Anymore,” signed by William H. Cogswell, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Facsimile of last Confederate newspaper printed in Vicksburg, MS, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Poem, “The Wilderness,”, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Tract, “Write to the Soldiers", 1864 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Plan for children orphaned by the war, by T.S. Gold, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - National Peace Jubilee programs, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Decoration Day address, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Account of the end of the war, by Mary Gridley Ellinwood, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Confederate ten dollar bill, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
- World War I
  - Aid Agencies
    - Pamphlet, “The Armenian Atrocities,” published by the A.B.C.F.M., 1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Booklet, “The Opportunity and Test of American Christianity,” published by the Federal Council of the Churches of Christ in America, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Published items of the American Committee for Armenian and Syrian Relief, undated (Box 3, Folder 6-Mar)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from War-Time Commission of the Churches, regarding Armenian and Syrian crises, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - American Red Cross items, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 20-Aug)
  - Edward D. Cartwright Papers
    - Letter from Col. James Geddes, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence with Captain J.M. Burrell, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
    - Correspondence with Military Emergency Board, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 24-27)
    - Correspondence with Lt. Col. Chas. Smith, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 28-29)
    - Chevrons memo, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Receipts, 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    - Ammunition memo, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - “Second Indorsement” notice, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Home Guard membership card, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Cornwall Company, Connecticut Home Guard
    - Memo regarding drill date and NCO appointments, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Memo from Military Emergency Board to Capt. Robert, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Revised May muster rolls, and letter, returned to headquarters, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Newspaper clipping on members, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Blank receipt from Military Emergency Board, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Program for parade in Waterbury, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Outline for inspection and review, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Receipt for clothing and weapons, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Monthly drill report, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Honorable discharge of Frank L. Hart, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - General orders sent to Fifth District, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Tabulation of monthly drill reports, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Enlistment forms, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Military Emergency Board special orders, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Military property transfer sheets, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Ordinance transfer sheets, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Quartermaster supply transfer sheets, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Receipt of War-Camp Community Recreation Fund for West Cornwall donation, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Conn. Home Guard general orders and circular, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Letter sent to Col. James Geddes from commander, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Requisition for clothing and equipment paperwork, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Corrected order sent to Conn. Home Guard officers, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - General Order No. 12, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Copy of inspector’s report, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Memo regarding the suspension of drills, due to influenza epidemic, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Military Emergency Board booklet sent to Conn. Governor, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Muster roll of Co. K, 11th Sep. B’n, C.S.G., West Cornwall, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Results of rifle practice, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Letter from Military Emergency Board in response to discharge questions, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Military Emergency Board General Orders, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - General Orders, Co. K, 11th Sep. Bat., 1919 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Memo relating to mustering out of Cornwall Company, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Battalion drill instructional booklet, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Information Card No.2, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - List of Cornwall members, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Handwritten list of Cornwall names, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - List of provisions written on reverse of torn correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Manual of Interior Guard Duty, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Map of drill formations, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Monthly drill reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Newspaper clipping mentioning drilling on Sundays, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Program for target practice, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Riot drill instructional booklet and leaflet, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Saluting tutorial, intended for bulletin boards, undated (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - William C. Bierce enlistment papers, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - James R. Blake enlistment papers, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Home Front
    - Notice, “Stenographers and Typewriters Wanted", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Booklet, “How the War Came to America,” issued by Committee on Public Information, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Poster for Independence Day parade on the Cornwall Green, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Liberty Loan advertisement, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - War Library Bulletin Vol. I, No. 3, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Booklet, “The Second Liberty Loan and the Causes of Our War with Germany", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Official Bulletin Vol. I, No. 121, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Booklet on sermon suggestions related to Second Liberty Loan, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Invitation and ticket to Statewide War Rally at Hartford, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 10-Sep)
    - Circular announcing Liberty Loan Day in schools, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Informative post card on liberty bonds sent to Mrs. J.E. Calhoun, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Letter from fraternity, with aid card for members overseas, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from American Bible Society, about bibles for servicemen, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Invitation and ticket to Roosevelt War Rally sent to E.C. Starr, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - American Bible Society call for new testaments, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Circular letter sent to public and private schools, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from General War-Time Commission of the Churches, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Envelope addressed to E.C. Starr from Conn. State Council of Defense, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Invitation to speak sent to E.C. Starr from Conn. Council of Defense, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - The Atlanta University Bulletin Series II, No. 29, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Booklet on liberty loan bonds, What They Are and How To Buy Them, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Liberty Loan certificate of John E. Calhoun, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - United War Work Campaign receipt of Mrs. E.C. Starr, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Booklet, A Reference Book For Speakers, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Advertisement for The Literary Digest sent to E.C. Starr, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Advertising copy of patriotic songbook, “America’s Message", undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Booklet, Libraries For Our Soldiers and Sailors, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Bulletin sent to Congregational churches with recommended wartime reading list for parishioners, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Booklet, “Some War Songs of Uncle Sam and His Allies", undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Booklet, Commission on Training Camp Activities, undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Conn. Council of Defense pamphlet on how to conserve electricity, undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Cornwall’s certificate for reaching Victory Loan quota, undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Leaflet, “The Moral Meaning of the War,” distributed to ministers, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, regarding Liberty Loan Sunday activities, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Placard showing Cornwall’s Victory Loan allotment, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Liberty Loan bond application, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Cornwall Servicemen
    - Clipping naming W.L. Behm, John E. Mercier, and Louis F. Gekeler, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr by Ralph E. Corban, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Honorable discharge from the US Army of Walter J. English, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Newspaper article by US Army chaplain, Rev. Ralph H. Tibbals, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from Raymond Bunnell Waldron, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Honor roll of Litchfield County, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Newspaper clipping, “Drafted Men Leave", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Advertisement for Yale Alumni Weekly, mentioning students and alumni at war, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Fragment of unknown registration list, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Wartime Agriculture
    - Connecticut Agricultural College bulletins on wartime agriculture, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 47-50)
    - US Dept. of Agriculture Weekly Newsletter Vol. IV, No.51, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Text of address, “The Second Liberty Loan and the American Farmer", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - American Steel and Wire Co. report on “Cost of Growing Wheat", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Article on wartime potato crop, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Food Thrift Series pamphlet, “Help Feed Yourself", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - “Manual for Home Storage, Pickling, Fermentation and Salting Vegetables", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - US Dept. of Agriculture notice to “Save Your Own Vegetable Seed", 1917 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Booklet on “Urban and Suburban Food Production", undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Collection of “Prose Jingles” from Campaign on Food Conservation, undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Conn. Committee on Food Supply notice on the “Growth and Care of Garden and Field Beans", undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Conn. state agricultural notice, “Growing Corn for Grain", undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Letter and pledge card of the Junior US Food Army for girls, undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Food Production Statement, “Food Crops Must Be Increased", undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Newspaper clipping about canning demonstration at Cornwall Grange, undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - Pamphlet on “Food Thrift,", undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Sign for members of United States Food Administration, undated (Box 4, Folder 66)
- World War II
  - Connecticut War Council Dimout Regulations, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Article, “T.S. La Farge Lost With 30 on US Cutter", 1943 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Packet of information on Cornwall servicemen and women who served during World War II, 1943-1945 (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - Booklet from funeral of Capt. Ernest D. Clark, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - National War Savings Committee appointment of Florence Benedict, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Newspaper clipping on wartime rationing, undated (Box 4, Folder 72)
- Cold War
  - Ground Observer Corps. Skywatch Award, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 73)
- Memorial Information
  - Letter sent to E.C. Starr about building a Cornwall soldiers’ monument, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from US War Department, regarding military headstones, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, about resting places of Cornelius C. Parmelee and Walter J. English, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Newspaper article, “Graves of Revolutionary Soldiers Remembered", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Map of soldiers’ graves in Calhoun Cemetery, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Map of soldiers’ graves in North Cornwall Cemetery, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Notes on soldiers buried in Cornwall, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Miscellaneous
  - Newspaper article about the life of Greek Captain Colvocoresses, 1897 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Newspaper article on Litchfield County military history, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 56)